בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is כט. kaf tet. גוט
מועד. Gut moed. We pick up at the bottom of כח עמוד
ב. kaf chet amud bet.
We got to the debate of אביי Abaye and רבא. Rava. יאוש
שלא מדעת. Yeush shelo midaas. We פסקנ'ן pasken like אביי, Abaye, it's
not יאוש. yeush. So you have to assume the person is aware
of it. We had a debate about why the sheaves in רשות
הרבים, reshus harabbim, there's a difference between רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and
רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Either because מקום, makom, the place, normally is
a סימן, siman, but not if it's something that gets kicked around
in רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. That's רבא'ס Rava's approach. Or רבא'ס Rava's
approach that it actually had a סימן siman on it, but in
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim it would get trampled on. And we seem
to rule like רבא Rava that מקום makom generally is a סימן,
siman, except obviously if it's going to get kicked around. And also
again that would only be true in a case where something was
left behind as opposed to accidentally dropped. Okay, so then we are
now and we work through some of the details specifically about things
like the string of fish and other types of things, whether number
is a סימן, siman, weight is a סימן, siman, measures are a
סימן. siman. And we pretty much assumed that most of those things
that those things would generally be considered to be a סימן. siman.
Okay, so now we are, where are we?
בעי מיניה ba'i minei רב ביבי Rav Bibi מרב נחמן. meiRav Nachman.
The line starts with רב נחמן Rav Nachman in the bottom third
of כח עמוד ב. kaf chet amud bet. It's across from the
תוספות Tosafos במסכת. b'masechet. Okay, so the line starts with רב נחמן.
Rav Nachman. So רב ביבי Rav Bibi asked רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
מקום הוי סימן או לא הוי סימן? makom havi siman o lo
havi siman? So back to the question we asked before, is a
place a סימן siman or not?
Again in something that we can assume was accidentally left behind. אמר
ליה amar lei תני טו, tani tu, it's implicit in the ברייתא
braisa that we just did talk at the end of yesterday. מצא
חביות של יין ושל שמן ושל תבואה, matza chaviyot shel yayin veshel
shemen veshel tvuah, if you find barrels with wine or oil or
grain, and again these would be like standard barrels and they'd be
filled so the quantity isn't a סימן, siman, the barrel isn't a
סימן, siman, ושל גרוגרות ושל זיתים, veshel grogrot veshel zeitim, or of
pressed
figs or of olives, הרי אלו שלו, harey eilu shelo, you can
keep it. These are all just like standard objects and therefore you
can keep it. Okay, how's that relevant? ואי סלקא דעתך דמקום הוי
סימן, ve'ee salca da'atach d'makom havi siman, if the place were a
סימן, siman, יכריז מקום, yichriz makom, say where they found them. This
is not something that slips out of your pocket. This is not
something that gets kicked around. So this is something that you leave
behind. You leave behind a big barrel of olives. So why not
just say here's where I left it behind? So the fact that
you can't indicates that against רבא Rava that מקום makom is not
a סימן. siman. אמר רב זביד, Amar Rav Zavid, no, let's come
to defend רבא, Rava, הכא במאי עסקינן בריקסא דנהרא. hacha b'mai askinan
b'riksa denahara. We're talking about it's at the edge of the river.
Basically it's like at the port. Okay, go down to the port
and you find a big box of barrels. That's where they're loading
up the barrels on and off of the ships. Okay, so therefore
to say that you lost a barrel of olives or of or
of wine at the port is not a great סימן. siman. So
but in general it would be. אמר רב מרי, Amar Rav Mari,
מאי טעמא אמרו רבנן ריקסא דנהרא לא הוי סימן? mai ta'ama amru
rabbanan riksa denahara lo havi siman? Why is it that the rabbis
say that like the edge of the river, again this is specifically
the place where the port where ships load and unload is not
a סימן? siman? דאמרינן ליה, d'amrinan lei, we say to him, כי
היכי דאתרמי לדידך, ki heichi de'itrami lidiydach, the same way by you
know it chanced by you that you left your barrel of wine
there, אתרמי נמי לחברך, itrami nami l'chavrach, your friend also could have
left his barrel of wine there. Okay, it's there's nothing special about
having a barrel of wine you know left by the edge of
the port. Or also maybe you're just being a lucky guesser. You
know it's not a proof that it's yours.
איכא דאמרי ika d'amri some say, אמר רב מרי, amar Rav Mari,
מאי טעמא רבנן מקום לא הוי סימן? mai ta'ama rabbanan makom lo
havi siman? No, that
the conclusion was not the רב זביד's Rav Zavid's response, but the
conclusion was the first thing we said, that מקום makom is not
a סימן siman and we don't want to say it's talking about
a special case. We want to say it represents that in general
מקום makom is not a סימן siman against רבא. Rava. So why
is that? So דאמרינן ליה, d'amrinan lei, we say to anybody who
can identify, oh I left it you know on the corner of
239th and Henry Hudson, so we say to him, כי היכי דאתרמי
לדידך האי מקום אתרמי נמי לחברך האי מקום. ki heichi de'itrami lidiydach
hai makom itrami nami l'chavrach hai makom. There's nothing special about that
place. Now of course again there might not be somebody else could
have left something there. But of course you know it's the exact
intersection of that place and this object. So it's one thing to
say types of things when those objects are very common. I don't
know I lost 20 dollars you know and on the corner of
this street. Okay, a lot of people could have dropped 20 dollars
right.
If I say I really don't think so.
You don't think so?
A lot of people drop the same amount of money that you...
Okay, anyway, but clearly there are things there are types of things
which are relatively common whatever. There are other types of things right
which are anyway the point being that the intersection and that's the
question that Michael asked yesterday which is a good one, you know
one thing by itself might not be a סימן siman but the
intersection of those things should be. Anyway, this is a way of
looking at this against
רבא. Rava. is not a סימן. siman. But let's remind ourselves that
רבא Rava says as a general rule מקום makom is a סימן
siman in something that did not fall, something that was left there,
okay, so you know where it was left and which does not
get kicked around and moved around. Okay, so that's the question, two
ways of understanding, either this indicates מקום makom is not a סימן
siman because or that this is a special case of the port,
of the edge of the river. Now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay,
ההוא גברא דאשכח כופרא בי מעצרתא. Hahu gavra de'ashkach kufra be'ma'atzarta.
There was a certain person who found pitch in the place of
the, you know, where it was like the, I don't know, the
processing
space, the place, מעצרתא ma'atzarta normally is like מעצרתא, ma'atzarta, the like
pressing floor, but you don't make pitch in a pressing floor. Wherever
it was, in a place where you know that they would have
that they would process pitch and he left some behind, okay? So
אתא לקמיה דרב, Ata lekamei de'Rav, so he came to רב, Rav,
אמר ליה זיל שקול לנפשך, Amar lei zil shekol lenafshacha, go keep
it for yourself,
okay? So why? Didn't have a סימן, siman, presumably I don't know
we were assuming that מקום makom was not a סימן, siman, that
was sort of like the edge of the river type of scenario,
a lot of people could have left it there, so there was
nothing specific about that.
When you say that that's exactly a weird thing since you don't
really leave it.
I don't know, well that doesn't seem to be, I don't know,
maybe, but it doesn't seem to be the case, seems to be
that was a standard type of a thing that was doing that
was that you know that would have been found there, so it's
not a, there was no סימן siman on it and the מקום
makom presumably was not a סימן, siman, go take it for yourself.
אתא לקמיה דרב, Ata lekamei de'Rav, saying to רב, Rav, אמר ליה
זיל שקול לנפשך. Amar lei zil shekol lenafshacha. חזייה דהוה קא מחסם.
Chazeiyei dehava ka mechassem. He saw that he was hesitating. אמר זיל
פלוג ליה לחייא ברי מיניה. Amar zil pelog lei le'Chiya beri minei.
So give half of it to my son, okay? You don't want
it, you're hesitating, fine, I'll take it. Or he said that because
I'll prove to you I'm okay with it, right? It's not גזל,
gezel, you'll take give half to my son and then you'll at
least take the other half, you'll feel good and you'll feel confident
that it's okay to take. לימא קסבר רב מקום לא הוי סימן?
Lima kasavar Rav makom lo havei siman?
So let's say מקום makom there was not a סימן, siman, right?
That's question, maybe it was unusual, what's the story there about the
מקום? makom? אמר רב אבא משום יאוש בעלים נגעו בה. Amar Rav
Abba mishum ye'ush be'alim nague ba.
No, okay, again, again more like Michael said, not like I was
saying, maybe the מקום makom was unusual to be there, but why
was it not a סימן? siman? Because it was clear that the
owner had been there a long time, the owner had clearly given
up hope of ever retrieving it. How do you know? דחזא דקדחי
בה חלפי. De'chaza de'kadchei ba chalfi. They saw that it had been
like covered with like rust, you know, so mold or something. So
clearly it had been abandoned for a long time. Now wait, what
is it, bees?
Weeds? Oh I'm sorry, weeds. Okay, weeds had grown on it. Okay,
so it's clear that it had been abandoned for a long time
and the owner. Now again, how long? At what stage do we
assume? You know some people don't give up hope of retrieving something
for a very long time. So it's not exactly clear to me
how you do the translation of like of how much time, you
know, in terms of something. Again, maybe if something's the only סימן
siman was a מקום, makom, maybe people are more ready to be
מיאש mitya'esh when the סימן siman is a much more identifying thing,
right? If I lost my wallet and it has my name in
it or something like that, you know, am I, I don't know,
would we say after a certain period of time? What would that
period of time be? Maybe it's a, it's a much more identifying
mark, you know, we'd be less prepared to say it. So that's
interesting and we'll see more about that later today as well, this
question about whether time can be a factor in something that normally
you'd say would be a סימן. siman. Yes, Michael.
No it's an interesting point. I mean cause sometimes the more valuable
it is, the longer it takes you to get back, the more
quickly you'll be מיאש. mitya'esh. In other words, like let's say you
know, you think, okay someone found my wallet, a week, maybe a
week, but weeks. They already took it. You know I'm, I'm already
you know like, credit cards, they stole my identity, you know all
those things you'd be doing already.
Right. Right, yeah, I might, I know, I don't know how to
factor all those things in. Okay.
Yes.
But the other
thing is essentially the
alternative.
But the other thing I'll say which is interesting though is again
the question about trying to make judgments of this particular person versus
of the circumstances, right? So here it has the right circumstances, it's
מקום, makom, it's a סימן siman or whatever, you know but because
we're going to assess, I mean it has like the right you
know indicators that we normally would say you have to return it,
but we're going to assess in this particular context there was יאוש
ye'ush and that's going to override. Right, which is consistent with אביי,
Abaye, יאוש שלא מדעת לא הוי יאוש, ye'ush she'lo mida'at lo havei
ye'ush, which is you at the end of the day care about
the person's more conscious thoughts about this issue. But it is interesting
when, how often can we look at context, you know, and still
try to have regular rules within the הלכה. halacha. Right. What,
we פוסק pasken like, like רבא Rava that מקום makom is not
a סימן. siman. That מקום makom is, מקום makom is a סימן
siman against רבא. Rava. מקום makom is a סימן siman if it's
something that is not kicked around and that is indicated that it
was forgotten there as opposed to something that was dropped. Okay, back
to the משנה, mishnah, רבן שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Rabban Shimon ben
Elazar omer, רבן שמעון בן אלעזר Rabban Shimon ben Elazar says, anything
כלי אנפוריא klei anporya is,
you know, you can keep. So מאי אנפוריא? Mai anporya? What's אנפוריא?
anporya? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל כלים חדשים שלא שבעתם. Amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Shmuel kelim chadashim she'lo seva'atam. שבעתן העין. sav'atan ha'ayin. They're
like new clothes that clearly the person you assume the person literally
the eye has not been sated with them yet. The person has
not yet come to identify them, hasn't does not have a טביעות
עין. tvi'at ayin. They're not yet at a stage where the owners
can say that they recognize them even in the absence of a
סימן. siman. Brand new fresh clothes off the rack. Again, how do
you know exactly how fresh they are and how you know how
recent they were off the rack? Maybe you bought it in the
store and you've been hanging it in your closet. Maybe it's still
in the box. You bought it in the store and you've been
hanging it in your closet appreciating it untouched in its plastic. How
do you know how to measure whether it's שבעתן העין sav'atan ha'ayin
or not? Anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with this.
And then we're also going to see what the debate might be
about this because it's only רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar. היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case? אי דאית בה סימן,
ei de'it beh siman, if it has a סימן, siman, כי לא
שבעתן העין מאי הוי? ki lo sav'atan ha'ayin mai havay? Even if
you have not yet gotten a chance to recognize it, who cares?
You have a סימן, siman, give a סימן. siman. אי דלית בה
סימן, ei deleit beh siman, and if it doesn't have a סימן,
siman, כי שבעתן העין מאי הוי? ki sav'atan ha'ayin mai havay? So
what if you recognize it? The question is how can we trust
you? This gets back to the whole issue
before about טביעות עינא. tvi'at eina. So good, you say you recognize
it. How do I trust you?
לעולם דלית בה סימן, le'olam deleit beh siman, there's no סימן. siman.
נפקא מינה, nafka mina, and here it's important, there is a time
you can return an אבידה aveidah without a סימן siman and you
do trust
a person: לאהדורי לצורבא מרבנן בטביעות עינא. le'ahadurei letzurba me'rabanan betvi'at eina.
You can return it to a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham if he
says he recognizes it even though he doesn't give a סימן. siman.
Basically, you can trust them to be honest about these things. Other
people you can't, but a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham you can trust,
which is very interesting. Normal person you have to be suspicious of,
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham you don't have to be suspicious of.
Normal person or just like your friend you know him well kind
of thing? Or do they really mean that specific?
That's an interesting question. If I know that you,
and the נפקא מינה nafka mina would be because then I would
be possibly, I mean it's my own money I could do with
it what I want if it's not yours, but the point is
no, if I trust you, I'm possibly giving up something that a
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham is going to come and say that it
was his. So that's a good point if you personally trust the
guy. There is places in הלכה, halacha, especially here where we do
that. I think about נאמנות, ne'emanut, רב משה Rav Moshe has a
famous תשובה teshuva about can you trust somebody
to say something is כשר, kasher, to have been a משגיח, mashgiach,
and not that it's industrial כשרות. kashrut. Somebody wanted to know about
eating at somebody's house where the person wasn't observant, but I think
it was a case about her father and she had absolutely no
question that her father was going to be מקפיד makpid and make
sure all the הלכות halachot were followed, but technically he wasn't
observant. Can she trust him that the food is
כשר? kasher? רב משה Rav Moshe basically says, again I'm just paraphrasing
here don't פסקן pasken based on this,
but he basically says if you're totally certain that it's כשר kasher
then you don't need to satisfy formal requirements of נאמנות ne'emanut in
terms of that. So it is possible, that's an interesting point, if
you really trust the person maybe that would also be a case.
לאהדורי לצורבא מרבנן בטביעות עינא. le'ahadurei letzurba me'rabanan betvi'at eina. You would
have to return it in case some תלמיד חכם talmid chacham comes
along. Now of course the נפקא מינה nafka mina about this is
that that means that you have to, if you find something with
no סימן, siman, according to at least רבי שמעון בן אלעזר—it's Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar not clear we פסקן pasken like רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, but according to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר,
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, well actually it's not clear which way we
disagree with him,
are we more מחמיר machmir or more מקיל meikel than him—but according
to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar if you find
something that presumably the owners will have gotten to know and recognize,
then even without a סימן siman you have to hold on to
it in case a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham will come and say
that it's his. That might only be in places where there are
a lot of תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim around. No, I'm serious. In
a place where it might have dropped from a תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham who you would believe to say it's theirs, you would have
to hold on to this. This greatly expands the universe of אבידות
aveidot that you have to hold on to. Forget all the discussions
of סימן. siman. Any type of object that the owner might recognize,
if it's possible it came from a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham or
reasonable that there's תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim around here, you'd have to
hold on to it because the תלמיד חכם talmid chacham will come
and say he recognizes it.
Doesn't that contradict what we said before, let's say it's money?
Right. No, money is not something that there would be a טביעות
עין tvi'at ayin on, but a wide range of things don't have
a סימן siman that there could be a טביעות עין tvi'at ayin
on.
Like if you find it in Riverdale you'd have to?
Right! Any place that has like a ישיבה yeshiva or anything like
that. It's true.
So let's take a look. בטביעות עינא. betvi'at eina. שבעתן העין קים
ליה בגוויה, sav'atan ha'ayin kaim leih begaveih, once the eye has been
sated with it he then really
can identify it ומהדרינן ליה umahadrinan leih and we return it. כי
לא שבעתן לא קים ליה בגוויה ולא מהדרינן ליה, ki lo sav'atan
lo kaim leih begaveih velo mahadrinan leih, but if not at that
point then he obviously does not really
identify it and you don't have to return it to him. דאמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, de'amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, הני
תלת מילי עבידי רבנן דמשנו במילייהו, hanei telat milei avidi rabanan demishanu
bemileihu, that in these the rabbis, the תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, will
only sort of
fudge the truth in three things and therefore they're very, very careful
to always be totally honest except in these. three areas, so therefore
in any other area you can totally trust them. What are these
three things?
במסכת ובפורייא ובאושפיזא. be'masechet uve'puraya uve'ushpiza. So there's a whole question what
this means. רש"י Rashi says it means if somebody says to him,
hey have you learned, you know, בבא קמא? Bava Kamma? He says
no, I haven't learned that, okay? Because then you're supposed to be
modest. Others say the word that what it means is that if
somebody asks him a question in something, you know, like, hey what's
the הלכה halacha about so and so, you know, you're supposed to
say I don't know, you know, like לעולם למד לשונך לומר איני
יודע. le'olam lammed leshoncha lomar eini yodea. But presumably not if somebody
actually needs a פסק psak right now. Somebody's just סתם stam talking
you know, I don't know, I haven't חזר chazered it recently, or
whatever, some type of a thing like that, you know, it's a
statement of modesty. Okay? ובפורייא, Uve'puraya, פורייא puraya literally means the bed.
So רש"י Rashi basically says, yeah, no, פורייא puraya is just the
Aramaic word for bed. רש"י Rashi says I don't know. So anyway,
רש"י Rashi says it means they say have you slept with your
wife last night, which is like crazy, who asks that question? So
תוספות Tosfot says it means like, oh did you sleep in this
bed? And that even there you're supposed to say no because like
who knows, you know, what type, what was left behind in the
bed or whatever.
So, the מהרש"א Maharsha is very cute, says that maybe פורייא puraya
here means פורים, Purim, which is also the Aramaic word for פורים.
Purim. And he says, it's very funny. He says because the גמרא
Gemara says you're supposed to get so drunk on פורים Purim עד
דלא ידע בין ארור המן לברוך מרדכי. ad d'lo yada bein arur
haman l'baruch mordechai. So a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham is able to
say I don't know the difference between ארור המן arur haman and
ברוך מרדכי baruch mordechai even if he's not so drunk. Okay? So
that's he's allowed to fudge a little bit. Okay? Anyway,
ובאושפיזא uv'ushpiza is about your host, that you're not supposed to, if
you, people are asking you, oh like you know how welcoming is
this guy as a host, you're not supposed to, you're supposed to
fudge it a little and say hey it's not so great, if
you're, if you're concerned that these people will then go and take
advantage of him. You know, they hear that he's so welcoming or
whatever, they're going to go take advantage of him so then you're
supposed to downplay it. So those are the only three things that
they like fudge. So everything else they're super careful about. Okay? By
the way, what I don't understand about this by the way, I
must say, you know, first of all it's an interesting question in
general right, about how much is there an איסור issur to tell
a lie? From this and other גמרות Gemaras it sounds like there
is not, you know, even though it says מדבר שקר תרחק, mi'devar
sheker tirchak, that's in the context of judges. There's not really clear,
you know, about how אסור assur it is just lying you know,
again, not in a way that doesn't hurt people in a way
that's not stealing money, you know, how much is there really a
problem at all about telling a lie? It does not seem so
much. There's other גמרות Gemaras as well that you're allowed to be
משנה מפני דרכי שלום meshaneh mipnei darchei shalom or something like that.
Right, exactly. So anyway, that's number one. But number two is that
like, is that like here, by saying that this is yours, you're
basically taking it away from somebody else, right? By saying you identify
it, you're taking it away either by from the rightful owner who
could identify it or from the finder who would be allowed to
keep it if nobody could identify it. So like why, you know,
like why do we have to prove how honest the rabbis are
that they don't tell white lies except in these three areas? Even
if they told a lot of white lies or whatever, like why
would we suspect them of, you know, misidentifying an object as theirs,
which is really gets into stealing essentially. You know? So it's like
maybe the point is that if you in general are, fudge things
a little bit, you know, so you're also just not as rigorous
for your own standards, like you convince yourself that you recognize it
even when you don't recognize it. Right? You could sort of see
that, yeah, that looks familiar, that looks like mine, you know, but
if you have a lot of, if you're usually very rigorous about
being really fully honest then you won't be, you know, tricking yourself
either in these cases. So anyway, so a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
at least we can trust them. So מאי נפקא מינה? mai nafqā
mīnnāh? אמר מר זוטרא Amar Mar Zutra לאהדורי ליה אבידה בטביעות
עינא. le'ahadurei lei aveidah bitviut eina. So this statement of רב יהודה
אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel that they only fudge these three
things, the גמרא Gemara said, in the different discussion that we're inserting
here, what's the implication, why's it important to know that they don't
fudge other things? That they, we can trust them to return an
אבידה aveidah if they say they recognize it. אי ידיענא בה דלא
משני אלא בהני תלת, I yadinan beh d'lo meshaneh ela behani telat,
if we know somebody only fudges in these three areas, מהדרינן ליה,
mahadrinan lei, we return it to him. ואי משני במילי אחריני, V'ei
meshaneh be'milei acharinei, but if he fudges in other areas, לא מהדרינן
ליה, lo mahadrinan lei, we do not return it. Okay. מר זוטרא
חסידא, Mar Zutra Chasida, now מר זוטרא חסידא, Mar Zutra Chasida, איגניב
ליה כסא מאושפיזא.
igniv lei
kasa mei'ushpiza.
So a silver goblet was stolen from his like inn. חזינהו להו
בר בי רב, Chaza'inhu le'hu bar bei rav, he saw a certain
student of the rabbis. Okay, so here's a, so here you go,
rabbinic student that normally you would trust, we just got through saying
that you could trust them even for saying they recognize something. Here's
somebody stole something and he saw this rabbinic student דמשי ידיה ונגיב
בגלימא דחבריה. demashi yadei venagiv beglima dechavreih. He washed his hands and
he dried it on somebody else's, you know, cloak that was hanging
up in the cloak closet, in the coat closet. אמר היינו האי
דלא איכפת ליה אממונא דחבריה. Amar: Hainu hai d'lo ichpat lei amamona
dechavreih. Ah, this must be the guy who stole it, this is
the guy because clearly he's not concerned about somebody else's property. He's
willing to dry his hands on somebody else's coat. כפתוהו, Kaftuh, they
seized him, ואודי, ve'odei, and he admitted it. Okay. So therefore it's
an interesting juxtaposition, right? Oh, this must be the guy who stole
it. This is the guy because he's clearly he's not concerned about
somebody else's property. He's willing to dry his hands on somebody else's
coat. כפתיה ואודי, Kaftei v'odei, and he admitted it. Okay, so therefore
it's an interesting juxtaposition, right? Because on one hand we say, oh,
תלמידי חכמים Talmidei chachamim in general they're super honest, you know, they
will you can trust them to say they recognize something and here,
not all תלמידי חכמים Talmidei chachamim are so honest. This guy actually,
you know, goes ahead, steals some silver goblets. Okay. תניא, Tanya, we
learned in a ברייתא, Braita, מודה רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Modeh Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar. Anyway, what's not clear here is
that what did the רבנן Rabbanan say against רבי שמעון בן אלעזר?
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar? רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
says if it's לא טביעות עין, Lo tvi'as ayin, then you're allowed
to keep it. So what do the חכמים Chachamim say? Presumably, everybody
agrees if there's no סימן siman and לא טביעות עין lo tvi'as
ayin you're allowed to keep it. So what? Are the חכמים Chachamim
more מחמיר, machmir, you know, are the חכמים Chachamim saying that even
if it is טביעות עין tvi'as ayin you're allowed to keep it
and they don't buy into this טביעות עין? tvi'as ayin? Like it's
not exactly clear what the debate is. Okay, anyway, מודה רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר בכלים חדשים שטביעות עין שחייב להכריז. Modeh Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar be'keilim chadashim she'tvi'as ayin she'chayav lehachriz.
But he does agree that when you are, you know, you do
recognize them that then you do have to announce, I mean, when
they have gotten to a point where they can be identified, you
know, even without a סימן, siman, when there's a טביעות עין, tvi'as
ayin, then they have, you have to announce them. ואלו הן כלים
חדשים. Ve'eilu hein keilim chadashim.
Wait, how a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham might be able to identify
it?
Yeah, we're back to what we said before. Yeah. It's just the
משנה mishna said it in a funny way. He said שלא טביעות
עין shelo tvi'as ayin you're allowed to keep, right? Presumably, everybody agrees
to that. Brand new, no סימן, siman, of course you're allowed to
keep. So the way it's framing it, it's funny. מודה רבי שמעון.
Modeh Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees that if you did
get to recognize, if they are, if they are something that you,
you know, your eye would have been ensnared with, that now could
be recognized by the owner, you have to announce it. So what
do the חכמים Chachamim say? You have to announce it all the
time? Even if it's brand new? Even without a סימן? siman? It's
very bizarre what the position of the חכמים Chachamim is supposed to
be. Anyway, מודה רבי שמעון בן אלעזר בכלים חדשים שטביעות עין שחייב
להכריז, אלו הן כלים חדשים שלא טביעות עין. Modeh Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar be'keilim chadashim she'tvi'as ayin she'chayav lehachriz, eilu hein keilim chadashim shelo
tvi'as ayin. The following ones are ones that we could say are
brand new that you're allowed to keep, שאינו חייב להכריז. she'eino chayav
lehachriz. You don't have to announce. כגון בדי מחטין וצינורות ומחרוזות של
קרדומות, Kegon badei mactin ve'tzinoros u'machrozos shel karduymos, for example, branches or
like, you know, things that, from which hang,
not literal branches, figurative branches, from which hang needles and like little,
little spinning forks, ומחרוזות של קרדומות u'machrozos shel karduymos
and like a type of a string of, what do they say,
that string of hammers or something? Strings of axes? That's bizarre. Anyway,
כל אלו שאמרו. kol eilu she'amru. Okay, all these that they said,
אימת מותרין, eimas mutarin, when are they permissible? It's such a funny
example. Since when, I don't understand, what does that mean that it's
brand new? Let's say it's been sitting in my house. Does it
just mean like it's a type of a thing that doesn't change
until I start using it? And then when I start using it,
it'll, the use will be obvious, you know? And then or maybe
I'll start, maybe I will have removed, I'm going to, I'm guessing
it's sounding like if I haven't taken the packaging off. You know,
that's why it gave examples of something that multiple things are hanging
from something. Like you, you buy like a thing that has like,
you know, five different sized hatchets hanging from it. So as long
as it's all that way, once you start using it, you start
taking the hatchets down. Once you start using it, you start taking
like the needles down. So if they're still all suspended there, it
means almost like you haven't unwrapped it from its packaging. Okay, that's
my sense of what's going on here.
Okay.
So
what's the difference if it's like the exception of once you start
using it, then you recognize it?
Yeah, then you'll get to, get טביעות עין tvi'as ayin somehow, you
know. Right, but again, how do you know, like, you know, and
if it's been hanging up and I've been looking at it this
whole time? But I guess if I haven't unwrapped the packaging, it
doesn't look different than anybody else's hammer that hasn't ever been used,
you know. I don't know, but it doesn't say that you haven't
used, right? טביעות עין Tvi'as ayin just sounds like you've been looking
at it for a long time. So I don't know exactly how
to measure these things. Okay. כל אלו שאמרו אימת מותרין, בזמן שמצאן
אחד אחד, אבל מצאן שנים שנים חייב להכריז. Kol eilu she'amru eimas
mutarin, bizman she'metza'an echad echad, aval metza'an shnayim shnayim chayav lehachriz.
If you find individual, now does it mean an individual, you know,
needle or hammer because it just, or does it mean an individual
like collection because we just, you know? But if you found two
or whatever then you have to announce because then we get to
the issue of number. מאי בדי? Mai badei?
What is a בד, bad, this, this thing from which you suspend
needles? שוכי. Shochei.
So literally it means like a branch.
It's figurative. ואמאי קרו ליה בדי? Ve'amai karu lei badei? So why
is it called בדי? badei? דבר דתלו ביה מידי בד קרו ליה.
Davar de'talu bei midi bad karu lei. Something to which things are
suspended from is called a בד. bad. כי הא דתנן התם, Ki
ha de'tnan hasam, like we taught over there in סוכה, Sukkah, so
here's something relevant, עלה אחד בבד אחד. aleh echad b'vad echad.
We're talking about a, when an ערבה aravah is still good even
if there's just one leaf coming out of like one בד bad
which is like the, you know, the place where it connects to
the branch. So anyway a בד bad is the place of suspension.
Anyway, moving on. וכן היה רבי שמעון. Ve'chein hayah Rabbi Shimon. So
that's the issue about טביעות עין tvi'as ayin which again it's not,
oddly, it's not clear to me what, you know, it's, the way
it's framed it sounds like the rabbis would say you always have
to return it, which is clearly not true. So presumably the rabbis
would say you wouldn't have to return it even as, you know,
even if it is טביעות עין tvi'as ayin without a סימן. siman.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, let's take a
look at תוספות Tosafos before we move on to the next point
about this. תוספות מודה רבי שמעון שטביעות עין. Tosafos Modeh Rabbi Shimon
she'tvi'as ayin. מדקאמר ומודה מכלל דרבנן אפילו לא טביעות עין חייב להכריז.
Mide'ka'amar u'modeh miklal de'rabbanan afilu lo tvi'as ayin chayav lehachriz. Right?
So that, which is a little bit bizarre. You always have to
return everything? I don't understand. וכן מצינו vechen matzinu ברבה בר בר
חנה b'Rabbah bar bar Chana דאמר בפרק קמא d'amar b'perek kama איתפש
עיני בגבי, itpish einei bi gabei, right? Remember the case of the
גט get where he says, oh I can recognize it, and you
return to me the גט get so that he recognizes it. ובגט
לא u'v'get lo טביעות עיני. tvi'ut einei. So and since when do
people spend a long time looking at a גט? get? דלא משיינא
גיטא בידא, d'lo m'shaina gita b'yada,
you don't leave it a long time. So תוספות Tosafot says אי
נמי ee nami that everybody agrees you return something if a תלמיד
חכם talmid chacham can identify it and the only difference is that
according to the חכמים Chachamim you assume that somebody can identify something
immediately, ורבי שמעון בן אלעזר v'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar says no, you
gotta at least give it a little amount of time. וקשיא v'kashya
דלא מתני גמרא רבנן זה בפירוש. d'lo matni Gemara rabanan ze b'ferush.
The רבנן rabanan never said, we have a whole פרק perek talking
about סימנים simanim and all of a sudden we're sneaking in this
idea that for תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim you return everything at all
times, even immediately you assume they can recognize something. ויש לומר v'yesh
lomar דמדי נקט במתניתין d'midei nakat b'matnitin כריכות, עיגולי דבילה, krichot, igulei
dveila מכרוזות, machruzot, וככרות v'kikarot הרי אלו שלו. harei elu shelo.
Since we gave all those examples in the משנה Mishnah that you
can keep it, אלו דברים אין דרכן להיות בהן טביעות עין. elu
devarim ein darkan lihyot bahen tvi'ut ayin. Those are things, food items
or whatever that nobody really gets to recognize. משמע mashma דדברים שדרכן
להיות בהן טביעות עין, d'devarim she'darkan lihyot bahen tvi'ut ayin,
things that are recognizable, בכל עניין חייב להכריז אפילו לא שהה כדי
טביעות עין. bechol inyan chayiv l'achriz afilu lo shaha k'dei tvi'ut ayin.
You always have to return it even if the person had not
had a lot of time to have it in his possession if
מצא במקום ששכיחי רבנן, matza b'makom d'shchichi rabanan, if it's a place
where there are תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim around.
כריכות, krichot, עיגולי דבילה igulei dveila, you can never have?
Yeah, did you really say you recognize your apple? You recognize,
but I don't know how to measure these things. Anyway, this of
course radically changes all the assumptions of the משנה, Mishnah, right? That
we're dealing with, you need a סימן, siman, you need a סימן,
siman, etc. Now we're finding out that רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar is actually the one that's מחמיר machmir or whatever,
he's the one that
limits the cases that you have to return it. According to the
רבנן, rabanan, if there're תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim around, forget סימן. siman.
You always have to assume that if it's any type of a
thing that somebody would be able to recognize, you would have to
hold onto it even if it's brand new, if it's a type
of thing that's recognizable. All right, so that's both pretty
radical shattering of our assumptions. Let's get back to sort of a
more normal territory. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: וכן
היה רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, v'chen haya Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
omer, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar also used to
say, המוצא מן הארי ומן הדוב ומן הנמר ומן הברדלס ומן זוטו
של ים ומשלוליתו של נהר, hamotza min ha'ari u'min hadov u'min hanamer
u'min habardelas u'min zuto shel yam u'mishlulito shel nahar, this is similar
to things we found before we discussed before.
If somebody saved something that was being attacked by a lion or
by a bear or by a נמר namer is a leopard? Yeah.
And a ברדלס bardelas is a hyena I think they say. Okay.
וזוטו של ים, u'zuto shel yam, the center of the ocean, ושלוליתו
של נהר, u'mishlulito shel nahar, or the middle of the river. המוצא,
hamotza, so we dealt with all those things before, that we said
before that those things are, you assume יאוש ye'ush without a סימן
siman and possibly even if the owner says they're not מתייאש, mitya'esh,
we presume יאוש ye'ush anyway, or we don't need יאוש ye'ush because
they're completely lost to normal people. Okay, but now we're going to
add things that are a little bit more normal, and this is
okay, which is the more common case. המוצא בסרטיא ופלטיא גדולה ובכל
מקום שהרבים מצויים שם. hamotza b'astratya u'faltya gdola u'v'chol makom she'harabim mtzuyim
sham.
Not only that, if you find in a סרטיא astratya or a
פלטיא faltya which are Greek words. סרטיא astratya is a major street
and a פלטיא, faltya, I think I'm getting that right, one of
them is a major street and the other is a major square.
Okay, and the פלטיא faltya is the major square.
If anybody's ever on Broadway or in Times Square...
Right. Have you ever seen the cardo in Jerusalem, the picture that
they have of it? That mosaic? Right, and they had this whole
street and then they had this whole big square in the middle
and they had those streets going into it. Right? So those major
streets are the סרטיאות astratyot and the big square where everybody gathers
are like the פלטיאות, faltyot, right. So basically like Broadway or Times
Square. What is it? Plaza? Plaza, yeah. Could be, yeah. So okay,
so if you find it in on like Broadway or Times Square
ובמקום שהרבים מצויים שם, u'v'makom she'harabim mtzuyim sham, a place where there's
a lot of people, הרי אלו שלו, harei elu shelo,
you can keep them even if it's got a סימן siman מפני
שהבעלים מתייאשין מהן. mipnei she'habealim mitya'ashin mehen. Because yes, because the owners
give up hope. Why do they give up hope? So the פשט
pshat here is, although we'll see in a minute some distinctions the
גמרא Gemara makes, it's sort of like finding in the middle of
the ocean. Now of course the difference here is that here somebody
can find it, but if there're so many people, it's in the
middle of Times Square, the likelihood that somebody found it who's not
going to be so honest and who's going to keep it for
himself and not return it to me is probably pretty darn high.
So therefore because there're so many people there, you have to return
it even if it's got a סימן... siman... You don't have to
return it. If you find it and you are honest, you don't
have to return it even if it has a סימן siman because
the owners immediately are מתייאש. mitya'esh. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu, they raised the question: כי
אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר ברוב כנענים. ki amar Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar b'rov Kna'anim. Again, the original גרסא girsa was not כנענים Kna'anim
here, it was like נכרים, Nochrim, but because the implication now that
we're going to be dealing with for the rest of the דף
daf today is that you don't return an object of non-Jews, you
have no obligation to return an object of non-Jews, so it was
all censored, we censored all the words of non-Jews and turned it
into
כנענים. Kna'anim. Okay, what does he have? Steinsaltz? Somebody, what does he
have? נכרים Nochrim or גויים? Goyim? נכרים. Nochrim. Okay, so anyway... So
is it ברוב נכרים, berov Nocherim, אבל ברוב ישראל לא, aval berov
Yisrael lo, but if it's mostly Jews there, then you're not מתייאש
mityaesh because then you assume a Jew will find it and will
return it, meaning here I'm sorry there's two assumptions here. Number one
is you don't return the object of a non-Jew and the other
is that you assume that if a non-Jew finds an object he
won't return it to you. It's very reciprocal, you know? So but
if a Jew finds the object he will return it to you.
So if you find it in a place where there are a
majority of non-Jews, there are two reasons why you shouldn't have to
return it. Number one is you can assume it came from a
non-Jew, so therefore you don't have an obligation to return it. Number
two is even if it came from a Jew, even if it's
a סימן siman and somehow you can identify that it did come
from a Jew, okay, nevertheless the owner will give up hope of
getting it back because he'll assume a non-Jew will have found it.
Okay, so are we talking to say that it's true in a
case where there's a majority of non-Jews makes sense? Would we say
it however או דלמא אפילו ברוב ישראל, o dilma afilu berov Yisrael,
even if it's a majority of Jews there? So it came from
a Jew, so why shouldn't you have to return it? Because the
owner, this would assert that the owner would give up hope of
getting it back because there are so many people there that the
likelihood that somebody found it who's not so honest, right, that's
even though you can definitely assume it came from a Jew and
the owner can assume a Jew will find it, but nevertheless maybe
because it's so many people there's יאוש yeush even in that case.
So that's the question. ברוב נכרים או אפילו אבל ברוב ישראל לא
או דלמא אפילו ברוב ישראל נמי אמר. berov Nocherim o afilu aval
berov Yisrael lo o dilma afilu berov Yisrael nami amar. So or
did he would even say it even in a majority of Jews
in that place? אם תמצי לומר אפילו ברוב ישראל נמי אמר, im
timtzi lomar afilu berov Yisrael nami amar, now if you would say
that even a majority of Jews you don't have to return it,
so פליגי רבנן עליה או לא פליגי רבנן. pleigi rabanan aleih o
lo pleigi rabanan. Did the Rabbis argue on him or not? ואם
תמצי לומר פליגי, ve'im timtzi lomar pleigi, let's say the Rabbis do
argue and say you do have to return it, ברוב ישראל ודאי
פליגי, berov Yisrael vadai pleigi, then they definitely would argue in the
case of the majority of Jews where you know it came from
a Jew and the person would assume maybe he would get it
returned, but ברוב כנענים פליגי נכרים פליגי או לא פליגי? berov Knaanim
pleigi Nocherim pleigi o lo pleigi? But would they also argue in
the case of the majority of non-Jews? Maybe even in that case
the owner wouldn't give up hope. ואם תמצי לומר פליגי אפילו ברוב
נכרים, ve'im timtzi lomar pleigi afilu berov Nocherim, and if they argue
even in the case of majority of non-Jews, so then you would
have Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar say when there's a big public thoroughfare
regardless of Jews or non-Jews you don't have to, and
the Rabbis would say regardless of Jews or non-Jews you do have
to return it. Okay, let's say they argue at opposite extremes. הלכה
כמותו או אין הלכה כמותו? halacha kemoto o ein halacha kemoto? Do
we rule like Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar or not? ואם תמצי לומר
הלכה כמותו, ve'im timtzi lomar halacha kemoto, and if we rule like
him, to what degree do we rule like him? דוקא ברוב נכרים,
davka berov Nocherim, do we only rule like him in the case
of majority of non-Jews? או דלמא אפילו ברוב ישראל? o dilma afilu
berov Yisrael? Okay, or even a majority of Jews? So we don't
know how far he would go and we don't know how far
we would פוסק pasken about this idea of a major thoroughfare or
a major plaza.
תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. המוצא מעות בבתי כנסיות ובבתי
מדרשות ובכל מקום שהרבים מצויים שם הרי אלו שלו מפני שהבעלים מתייאשין
מהן. hamotzei maot bevatei khnesiyot uvvatei midrashot uvkhol makom sheharabbim metzuyim sham
harei elu shelo mipnei shehabbalim mityaashin mehen. If you find money and
there's a majority and there's a lot of people there, right, it
says you can assume that the owner these big areas, these
big בית מדרש Beit Midrash or בית כנסת, Beit Knesset, places that
the masses gather, then you can assume that there's יאוש. yeush. So
that clearly seems to be רוב ישראל, rov Yisrael, who else gathers
in a בית מדרש Beit Midrash or בית כנסת? Beit Knesset? So
מאן שמעת ליה דאזיל בתר רובא? man sham'at leh de'azil batar rubba?
Who goes by the fact that there's like a not רובא rubba
does not mean a majority as opposed to minority, it means by
the fact that there's a lot of people that gather that that's
a relevant factor? רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. It's
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. שמע מינה אפילו ברוב ישראל נמי. shma mina
afilu berov Yisrael nami. So you see Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar would
say even if there's a majority of Jews, I mean not majority,
even if the place where
masses gather and they're Jews, even if they're Jews you don't have
to return it. לא הכא במאי עסקינן במפוזרין. lo hacha bemai askinan
bimfuzarin. No, no, no. We're talking here that there's no סימן siman
on the money, the money is scattered, and there's nothing to do
with the fact that it's a place that a lot of people
gather. Wait a minute, אי במפוזרין, ei bimfuzarin, if there's no סימן
siman and it's scattered, מאי איריא מקום שהרבים מצויים שם? mai irya
makom sheharabbim metzuyim sham? Then why did it say if you find
it in a place where the masses gather? אפילו אין רבים מצויים
שם. afilu ein rabbim metzuyim sham. Even if it would be a
place where the masses don't gather, there's no סימן. siman. אלא לעולם
בצרורין או צבורין. ela le'olam betzrurin o tziburin. It must be that
they're in a little little like bundle or they're piled up and
there is a סימן siman and nevertheless you don't have to return
it because it's a place where the masses gather. So you see
that it applies even to Jews. So the גמרא Gemara has an
interesting answer. הכא במאי עסקינן בבתי כנסיות של כנענים, hacha bemai askinan
bevatei khnesiyot shel Knaanim, so נכרים. Nocherim. Okay, it is in a
it is in a house of worship, not a synagogue, whatever, it's
in a house of worship of non-Jews. Now it's an interesting question
whether when the גמרא Gemara says that it is a בית כנסת
Beit Knesset of נכרים, Nocherim, does it literally mean it is a
house of worship? Because בית כנסת Beit Knesset actually means a house
of gathering, right? And actually there's גמרות Gemarot that discuss how the
fact that בתי כנסיות batei khnesiyot were used as basically houses for
they were not limited just to religious purposes, you know, as they
are nowadays, right, they were the Jewish community center or whatever was
also the בית כנסת. Beit Knesset. So anyway, so literally it means
a house of gathering. So we're not talking about Jewish synagogues, we're
talking about non-Jewish houses of gathering or houses of worship.
So the גמרא Gemara says בתי מדרשות מאי איכא למימר? Batei Midrashos
mai ika l'eimar? Okay, that's maybe for בית כנסת, Beis Knesses, but
how about a בית מדרש? Beis Medrash? That's a uniquely Jewish institution.
No, בתי מדרשות דידן דיתבי וקננין. Batei Midrashos didan de-yasvi u-kananin. You
find there are there are בתי מדרשות, Batei Midrashos, but it's a
place where non-Jews frequent. What are non-Jews doing frequenting these? So רש"י
Rashi says, well we hire non-Jews to sort of like watch them
at night. Of course I don't know why that would be רבים
מצויים שם rabbim metzuyim sham just because they're like sometimes watchmen. But
anyway, השתא דאמרת הכי, Hashta de-amart hachi, now that you've said this,
בתי כנסיות נמי דידן דיתבי בהו כנענים, Batei Kenesiyos nami didan de-yasvi
behu Kna'anim, it refers to the our synagogues but for some reason
non-Jews are, maybe we sold it to non-Jews, I don't know, we
rented it to them. Not exactly clear, but we're going to obviously
read that in a very דחוק dachuk way to say it's talking
about that it's being used by a large number of non-Jews, presumably
even a majority of non-Jews. Anyway, so that was pretty good prima
facie evidence that when we would say a place where masses gather,
you can keep it, applies even to Jews, but somehow we got
out of it to try to claim that's talking about a case
of non-Jews. Okay, תא שמע, Ta Shma, come and hear. מצא בה
אבידה. Matza bah aveidah. If you found in there an אבידה. aveidah.
Now this is a city that you found an אבידה aveidah in
a city that, and the question is what type of a city
is it or town? A town that's majority Jewish or majority not
Jewish. אם רוב ישראל חייב להכריז. Im rov Yisrael chayav l'hachriz. If
it is a majority of Jews, then you have to announce it.
אם רוב כנענים ונוכרים אינו חייב להכריז. Im rov Kna'anim u-nochrim eino
chayav l'hachriz. If it's a city that's a majority of non-Jews, you
don't have to return it. So מן דשמע ליה דאמר אזלינן בתר
רובא? Man deshamei leih de-amar azlinan basar ruba? Who's the one that
concerns himself about like whether you know the masses? So רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר. Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar. So רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rebbi
Shimon ben Elazar. שמע מינה כי קאמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר ברוב
כנענים אבל בישראל לא. Shma mina ki ka'amar Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar
be-rov Kna'anim aval be-Yisrael lo. So you see that when he says
if there's a large number of people, he's only talking about non-Jews,
because here it said if the majority is non-Jews you return it,
you don't return it, if the majority is Jews you do return
it. Now there's a little bit of a difference. The use of
the word רוב rov is confusing here. Until now we say רבים
מצויים. rabbim metzuyim. We're talking about specific places where the masses gather.
This is talking about, this משנה mishna here is not talking about
that you found it in a place where a lot of people
gather. It's talking about you found something in the middle of the
street, and you have to guess was this probably dropped by a
Jew or non-Jew. If it was dropped by a Jew I've got
to return it, if it was dropped by a non-Jew I don't
have to return it. Well, who is, what's the majority of the
population around here? If you found something on Riverdale Avenue, you could
probably say it's a reasonable likelihood that it was dropped by a
Jew, okay? If you found something down on Broadway, you know, at
the bottom of the hill, probably a reasonable guess that it was
dropped by a non-Jew. But neither of those mean that those are
places שרבים מצויים. she-rabbim metzuyim. Let's just try to assess based on
the local population who was the one who dropped it. So it's
a very strange proof that the גמרא Gemara is bringing here. But
the גמרא Gemara says, ah look, this is evidence that even when
we talk about the number of people, we focus on only, you
know, non-Jews makes it allowed, not Jews. So let's see what the
גמרא's Gemara answer is.
It's a matter of what they dropped, it's a, yeah well we're
going to, yeah well
we're
going to get to that too. Something that there might be some
issue about that, like is the thing itself evidence? But this is
the separate point. Until now we're talking about a places which are
major places of where the masses gather, you're afraid some unscrupulous person
is going to keep it. Here we're talking about assessing the local
population and determining who lost it. So in terms of assessing the
local population and determining who lost it, we're going to assume that
it's coming from non-Jews if the majority is non-Jews, and Jews if
the majority is Jews. So don't you see this means that according
to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar we distinguish between
Jews and non-Jews? שמע מינה כי קאמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר ברוב
נוכרים אבל בישראל לא. Shma mina ki ka'amar Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar
be-rov nochrim aval be-Yisrael lo. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הא
מני רבנן היא. Ha manni Rabbanan hi. No, this is the rabbis
who argue with רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar. So
תיפשוט מינה דמודו ליה רבנן לרבי שמעון בן אלעזר ברוב נוכרים? Tipshot
mina de-modu leih Rabbanan le-Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar be-rov nochrim? Okay, so
at least you see that when it is a majority of non-Jews,
they agree you don't have to return it, at least because then
you could assume it came from a non-Jew. אלא רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר, Ela Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar, you find here is רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר. Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar. ואפילו ברוב ישראל נמי. Ve-afilu be-rov
Yisrael nami. But he would say that if it's a place where
there are a lot of people gather, even if it's mostly Jews,
you also don't have to return it. So why here do you
return it in a case of רוב ישראל? rov Yisrael? והכא במאי
עסקינן בטמון. Ve-hacha be-mai askinan be-tamun.
This is something that is actually has been hidden away, buried away.
It's not something that just normally fell. So if right, so again,
remember, the reason we're saying that you would not have to return
it in a place where there are where it the masses gather
is because I'm going to assume, look, even though it's רוב ישראל
rov Yisrael and ישראל Yisrael is חייב chayav to return a lost
object, etc., you know, in the middle of Times Square there are
so many people that some unscrupulous person is going to find it
even if it's רוב ישראל. rov Yisrael. Ah, but let's say it
is not exposed. Let's say it's hidden. Let's say I buried it
somewhere, you know, I hid it away somewhere so that it shouldn't
be able to be found and then I forgot about it. Okay?
So in that case I'm not afraid some unscrupulous person took it.
So in that case I am allowed,
I do have to, I would have to be returned. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says ואי בטמון מאי עבידתיה גביה? Ve-i be-tamun mai
avidtei gabeih? So one minute, if it's if it was something that
you discovered that was buried, why are you doing picking it up
and trying to. to return it. והתנן Ve-ha-tenan we taught, מצא כלי
באשפה מכוסה, matza klee be-ashpah mechuseh, if you found something in a
garbage dump covered, לא יגע בו, lo yiga bo, don't touch it
because maybe because the owner may have hidden it away there. So
what are you doing taking it out and trying you know? It's
clearly was placed there by the owner, we should assume that he's
going to come back for it. It wasn't forgotten, it was placed
there intentionally. מגולה, meguleh, if it's exposed, נוטל ומכריז notel u-machriz go
in and announce it. So if the reason here you don't have
to be concerned that you know the owner is not concerned that
some unscrupulous person found it because it was buried, then what are
you doing taking and returning it? So the Gemara says כדאמר רב
פפא באשפה שאינה עשויה לפנות ונמלך עליה לפנותה. Kedamar Rav Papa be-ashpah
she-einah asuyah lepanot ve-nimlach aleha lepanotah. No, like he explains somewhere else
by the case of the ashpah that it would be different if
let's say it was a type of a garbage dump that normally
doesn't get cleared out and all of a sudden you decided to
clear it out and you found something that was buried. Okay? So
in that case you can't just leave it there. Because if you
leave it there,
then you're then you're exposing it, some next person is going to
take it and pocket it. Right? You uncovered something that was buried.
Okay, now normally you're supposed to leave it alone, the owner's going
to come back for it. But it but there are circumstances where
you can no longer leave it alone. It's now been exposed and
if you don't take it, the next person is just going to
take it and pocket it. So now you have a responsibility to
get it back to the owner. הכי נמי באשפה שאינה עשויה לפנות
ונמלך עליה לפנותה. Hacha nami be-ashpah she-einah asuyah lepanot ve-nimlach aleha lepanotah.
Okay, so we basically said the case is a case where it
was an object where the owner has not given up hope because
he does not he left it unexposed, he left it hidden, you
inadvertently exposed it and you can't leave it behind and now you
have to return it, so if it's רוב ישראל rov Yisrael you
have to return it. If it's רוב נכרים rov nochrim you don't
have to return it. Okay? The easier answer here that the Gemara
should have said is that you didn't find it in a place
of רבים מצויים. rabbim metzuyim. You found it in some normal street
and therefore if it's רוב ישראל rov Yisrael you return it, if
it's רוב נכרים rov nochrim you don't return it. Okay, but anyway
that's at least what we're saying you know we that's at least
how we answered it in terms of this case about that you
expose something. ואיבעית אימא Ve-iba'it eima and if you I want I
can tell you לעולם רבנן le-olam rabanan it is the Rabbis who
basically argue on Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar and say that maybe you
do have to return things. ומי קתני הן שלו? U-mi katani hein
shelo? Did we say when it's mostly non-Jews you get to keep
it? No. אינו חייב להכריז קתני. Eino chayav lehachriz katani. You don't
have to announce it. ויניח ויבא ישראל ויביא סימן ויטול. Ve-yanuach ve-yavo
Yisrael ve-yavi siman ve-yitol. Let you just leave it in your house
and the Yisrael will come and he'll give a סימן siman and
take it. Which means what? Which means what?
You find- it's a very fascinating middle position. Okay because again there's
two factors here. One factor is not finding it in a place
of where where a public gathering. It's just what is the majority
population? If the majority population is not Jewish I could assume it
came from a non-Jew and I don't have to return it. Jewish
I do have to return it. The other question is if it's
found in a place of
you know where where the masses gather, then the owner has given
up hope. All right. So what the Gemara here says is that
maybe the Rabbis would hold that in a place where the majority
population is not Jewish, right, here's the interesting thing. We said maybe
the Rabbis say that even if the majority is not Jewish you
have to return it. Why would you have to return it? Why
can't you assume that it came from a non-Jew if the majority
population is not Jewish? So the Gemara says, ah, here but here's
the thing. We assume the majority population is not- the majority population
is not Jewish so we so we assume it came from a
non-Jew so you don't have to go and announce it. But there's
still a minority possibility that it came to a Jew. What happens
if the Jew comes knocking at your door? You went ahead and
you pocketed it because you assumed it came from a non-Jew and
then a Jew comes knocking at your door and gives a סימן,
siman, right? Does all of a sudden what like the Halacha is-
I mean this is a really good question, right? From the perspective
of the loser, I lost my object, I have a סימן, siman,
I'm going to hope to get it back, I'm not מיאש. mi-ya'ish.
From the perspective of the finder, I'm assuming it's coming from a
non-Jew, I'm going to pocket it and not return it. Okay. But
let's say the assumption of the finder turns out to be wrong
and the owner comes and says I lost it. Does he have
to say sorry buddy, I had a right to assume it was
from a non-Jew and I pocketed it? Right? What do you say?
So here the Gemara- and now you could say that I have
as a- as the- as the owner don't have a right to
assume I'm going to get it back. If it's in a place
where the majority population is not Jewish, right, I have to say
look, every- we're all playing by the same rules and therefore the
finder is going to assume it came from a non-Jew, he's going
to have a right to keep it, so I don't have a
right to assume that I can ever get it back. Okay? That's
maybe possible. But maybe not. So here the Gemara allows for that
middle position. You don't have to announce it because you can assume
it came from a non-Jew. You don't have an obligation to be
proactive and to try to return it. On the other hand, if
it turns out that the owner is a Jewish and hasn't given
up hope, you're not entitled to keep it just because of the
assumptions you made which turned out to be wrong and then you
actually would have to return it.
Yeah, they don't discuss the idea of relations with the non-Jewish community,
you know, that idea of
returning things because of דרכי שלום Darchei Shalom and so on. Yes,
so that does pop up every now and then, but here we're
sort of talking from a strictly legal basis. Okay. Alright. So the
Gemara says like this.
Okay, תא שמע. Ta Shma. Does the individual have to know what's
a Jewish community or non-Jew community?
Yeah, I don't know, that's a good question too. Well, I mean,
the point is is that I think your presumption is you have
to return a lost object, so you would have to sort of
know that it's more not Jewish in order to be פטור Patur
from your obligation. תא שמע דאמר רב אסי מצא חבית יין בעיר
שרובה כנענים. Ta Shma de'amar Rav Assi matza chavit yayin b'ir sheruba
kena'anim. If you found a barrel of wine in a city that's
majority non-Jew, מותרת משום מציאה. Muteret mishum metziah. You're allowed to keep
it because you could assume it came from a
non-Jew, ואסורה בהנאה, v'asura b'hana'ah, but you can't drink it because or
get benefit from it because it's a wine of a non-Jew. בא
ישראל ונתן בה סימן. Ba Yisrael v'natan bah siman. Now a Yisrael
comes and gives a סימן siman and identifies it, מותרת בשתיה. muteret
b'shtiah. Now you can know that it came from a Jew, so
now you're allowed to drink it, but למוצאה, l'motzah, you can keep
it. Okay, that's the best! Thank you for giving me a סימן.
siman. Now I know it was yours, so it's the wine is
kosher, but because it was I found it in a city of
non-Jews, I'm allowed to keep it. Okay, so that does not allow
for that middle position. That basically means, like I said, one of
two things: either that well, it basically means that you as the
owner, you know, you can't say that you're not מיאש. meya'esh. Since
you know the owner since you know the finder's going to assume
it's from non-Jews, that means that regardless of what you say, we're
going to just assume that יאוש ye'ush exists because the finder has
a right to assume that he's allowed to keep it. Okay, so
the Gemara says, כמאן? ke'man? Who's this going like? כרבי שמעון בן
אלעזר. ke'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. It's like Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar that
says that you look at the population. Again, we switched from whether
it's a place of high traffic to the question of the local
population. So you're looking at the local population, is it Jewish or
non-Jewish? שמע מינה כי קאמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר ברוב כנענים, shma
mina ki ka'amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar b'rov kena'anim, that he's only
saying his idea when it's the majority is of people are not
Jewish, אבל ברוב ישראל לא, aval b'rov Yisrael lo, but if the
majority are Jewish, no. ואיבעית אימא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אפילו ברוב
ישראל נמי קאמר. v'iba'it eima Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar afilu b'rov Yisrael
nami ka'amar. So maybe we would say it both, that if it's
that even if it's even if it's a majority of Israel, but
again, that would be if you found it in a place of
high traffic. אבל
אפילו ברוב כנענים קאמר, aval afilu b'rov kena'anim ka'amar, where'd I lose
my place? ורב אסי סבר לה כוותיה בחדא ופליג עליה בחדא. v'Rav
Assi savar lah kevateih b'chada u'palig aleih b'chada. But Rav Assi held
like him regarding the majority non-Jews but not the majority Jews. So
now the Gemara says, וכי מאחר דאסורה בהנאה מותרת משום מציאה למאי
הלכתא? v'chi me'achar d'asura b'hana'ah muteret mishum metziah l'mai hilchata? If the
Gemara says that if you can't get benefit from it when you
assumed it was non-Jewish, what good does it do you to know
that you're allowed to keep it? Okay, so I'm allowed to keep
it, I can't even sell it, what good does it do for
me before the Jew gave a סימן? siman? אמר רב אשי לקנקניה.
amar Rav Ashi l'kankaneia. You can still use the barrel. Okay, you
have to spill out the wine. You can still use the barrel.
Anyway, so here what we're dealing with is a little bit of
a in one way it's a pretty straightforward Gemara, but it's a
little confusing because there's two completely separate issues. One is the population,
the local population, right? That Rabbi Shimon if the local population is
not Jewish, can you assume it came from a non-Jew and keep
it? Or do you have to assume like even so, maybe it
still came from a Jew and I have to return it? That's
one question. The other question is, if it's found in a place
of high traffic, then maybe even if it's Jewish, but if it's
high traffic, you have to assume that somebody that somebody took it
who's not going to return it. Two completely separate considerations. Within the
consideration of the non-Jewish population, like that's local, it seems like we're
getting to the point that before answering the high traffic issue, that
if the local population is not Jewish, you can assume it came
from a non-Jew and you are allowed to keep it. That seems
to be where the Gemara's going, that's the most recent talk about
the barrel of wine and so on. The interesting question then becomes,
let's say it turns out your assumption was false and the owner
comes and he gave a סימן. siman. Okay, so in one answer
we said, ah, well then you've got to return it. The other
answer is: no, it doesn't matter that your assumption was false. That
the owner should have been מיאש meya'esh anyway, because he should have
expected that I would have assumed it came from a non-Jew. And
that's similar to like the that's more the רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar position. That even after it turns out that
it was that the owner was Jewish and he gave a סימן,
siman, you don't have to return it since the majority population was
non-Jewish, the owner is assumed to be מיאש meya'esh and he can't
override that. Okay, so that's that's the issue about the about the
local population.
Would that matter with the wine, so does this person, even though
he couldn't drink it, he could sell it for a profit?
No, that would be if it was סתם יינם, stam yeinam, but
the Gemara here is assuming that it's that you know, that no,
I mean, the wine it would be אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah. It
wouldn't just be אסור בשתיה. assur b'shtiah. Yeah, אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah.
Okay, ההוא גברא דאשכח ארבע זוזי דציירי בסדינא. hahu gavra d'ashkach arba
zuzei d'tzayarei b'sadina. Now let's have a case. A certain person found
four zuz that were wrapped in a in a handkerchief ושדו בנהר
בירן, v'shadu b'nahar Biran, and they were thrown into the river Biran.
אתא לקמיה דרב יהודה. ata l'kameih d'Rav Yehuda. He came before Rav
Yehuda. אמר ליה זיל אכריז. amar leih zil achriz. Go announce it.
והא זוטו של ים הוא? v'ha zuto shel yam hu? What do
you mean? It's like the case we just talked about of Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar, which is ממש mamash like the middle of— of
the ocean, the middle of the river. So even if the owner
isn't מתייאש, mityaiesh, we should just assume יאוש. yei'ush. No, the גמרא
Gemara says no, שאני נהר בירן, shani nahar biran, the river of
Biran is different, כיון דמתקלי keivan d'mitkli because there are all of
these obstructions, לא מתייאש, lo mityaiesh, the owner is not מתייאש mityaiesh
because things wash up on the shore and get stopped, and we're
actually going to find that sometimes they stop it and then they
dam it up and then they and then they let the water
flow. So therefore the owner is not מתייאש. mityaiesh. וארובא כנעני מנהו,
v'aruba kanani minhu, but so what, but the majority population is not
Jewish, so shouldn't that be a basis for keeping it? שמע מינה
אין הלכה כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר אפילו ברוב כנעני, shma mina ein
halacha k'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar afilu b'rov kanani, should we see from
this that even if the majority population is not Jewish, you don't
rule like him and that you have to return it because he
was told to return this object? No, שאני נהר בירן דישראל סכרו
ליה וישראל כרו ליה. shani nahar biran d'Yisrael sachru lei v'Yisrael karu
lei. No, no, no, this river, the people that
basically close it and then reopen the sluice gates or whatever it
is, they dam it up and they release the water and then
they destroy the dam, it's all Jews. And since it's all Jews,
presumably a Jew lost it because who's around this river? Presumably it
fell out of the pocket of a Jew and presumably a Jew
will find it. So even if the local population is not Jewish,
the population that in this more very more local area, very specific
area is Jewish. So the גמרא Gemara says no, כיון דישראל סכרו
ליה אימור ישראל נפל. keivan d'Yisrael sachru lei eimar Yisrael nafal. Since
they're the ones who dig it, presumably it fell from a Jew,
וכיון דישראל כרו ליה לא מתייאש, v'keivan d'Yisrael karu lei lo mityaiesh,
and since they're the ones that dam it up, it's from a
Jew and since they're the ones that dig it up,
לא מתייאש, lo mityaiesh, they're not מתייאש mityaiesh because you assume a
Jew will find it and return it. רב יהודה הוה שקיל ואזיל
בתריה דמר שמואל בשוקא דבי דיסא. Rav Yehuda hava shakil v'azil batrei
d'Mar Shmuel b'shuka d'bei deisa. Rav Yehuda was going after Shmuel in
the marketplace of the place Be Deisa. אמר ליה מצא כאן ארנקי
מהו, Amar lei matza kan arniki mahu,
if you found a wallet here what would be the story? אמר
ליה הרי אלו שלו, Harei elu shelo, you'd be allowed to keep
it because presumably the most of the population in this, first of
all, there was a case where there were a lot of people
and number two, the majority population presumably was not Jewish. Okay, this
is actually a place where they sold deisa means like a porridge.
They sold like a pounded grain. בא ישראל ונתן בה סימן מהו?
Ba Yisrael v'natan bah siman mahu? Ah,
like the case before, fine, you can assume it's from a non-Jew,
but if a Jew gave a סימן siman what's the story? אמר
ליה חייב להחזיר. Amar lei chayav lehachazir. Oh, then you have to
return it. So he says תרתי? tarti? How can you say both?
If I was right to assume it was a non-Jew, then maybe
again we should assume the owner was מתייאש mityaiesh regardless, even if
it turns out that it did come from a Jew. אמר ליה
לפנים משורת הדין, Amar lei lifnim mishurat hadin,
and now we get this nice הלכה halacha which is a niche
that's been coming up, that if you know who the owner is
even if you might be entitled to keep it, you should return
it to do the right thing, to go beyond the letter of
the law. Okay. So yes, technically you're allowed to keep it, you
were allowed to assume it was a non-Jew and we therefore the
owner should have we should assume the owner was been מתייאש, mityaiesh,
but if it turns out the owner wasn't מתייאש mityaiesh and is
still looking for it and you know that it's his, you should
return it because of לפנים משורת הדין. lifnim mishurat hadin. כי הא
דאבוה דשמואל, Ki had'avu d'Shmuel,
like the father of Shmuel. אשכח הנך חמרי במדברא, Ashkach hanak chamrei
b'midbara, he found certain donkeys in the wilderness. ואהדרינהו למרייהו לבתר דבסר
תרי עסר ירחי שתא, V'ahadrinhu l'mareihu l'vatar d'vassar terei assar yarchei shata,
and he returned it to the owner after twelve months, לפנים משורת
הדין, lifnim mishurat hadin, going beyond the letter of the law. Now
what was beyond the letter of the law? So רש"י Rashi says,
well after twelve months you should assume that the owners were מתייאש.
mityaiesh. Okay, like the גמרא Gemara before about the case where the
grass grew on it. תוספות Tosafot says why do we assume people
are מתייאש mityaiesh getting back their donkeys after twelve months? It says
it goes back to that question about whether time is a factor
in יאוש. yei'ush. So תוספות Tosafot says no, the לפנים משורת הדין
lifnim mishurat hadin is that when you find animals after twelve months
you don't have to pay for their upkeep anymore. You're allowed to
sell them and keep the money and just return the person the
money and Shmuel's father kept on feeding the animal and taking care
of the animals and returned the animals themselves after twelve months after
the point that he was allowed to just transfer it into cash
and would have been able to return the cash.
So anyway here it's very important because here the גמרא Gemara says
yes, there are limits to returning lost objects, but there is an
idea of לפנים משורת הדין. lifnim mishurat hadin. Even if you're entitled
to keep it or entitled to like lower your upkeep expenses, you
should do the right thing and you should return it if you
know who the owner is. So let's just read a little bit
more.
רבא הוה שקיל ואזיל בתריה דרב נחמן בשוקא דגלדאי. Rava hava shakil
v'azil batrei d'Rav Nachman b'shuka d'gilda'ei. Rava was going after Rav Nachman
in the marketplace of like the the leatherworkers, the tanners. ואמרי לה
בשוקא דרבנן, V'amrei lah b'shuka d'rabbanan, or some say where the rabbis
were found. אמר ליה מצא כאן ארנקי מהו? Amar lei matza kan
arniki mahu? If you found a wallet here what's the story? And
if it's the place of רבנן, rabbanan, then it's a place where
the majority is Jewish. But again, it's a place where there are
where there are a lot of people. אמר ליה הרי אלו שלו,
Amar lei harei elu shelo, you're allowed to keep it. Now that's
important, that הרי אלו שלו harei elu shelo even in a marketplace
of רבנן rabbanan that presumably means that you're allowed even if רוב
ישראל, rov Yisrael, if it's a place of where the masses gather
you can assume יאוש yei'ush and you're allowed to keep it. בא
ישראל ונתן בה סימן מהו? Ba Yisrael v'natan bah siman mahu? Now
if a Jew came and gave a סימן siman what would be
the story? אמר ליה הרי אלו שלו, Amar lei harei elu shelo,
you're allowed to keep it. Okay, forget לפנים משורת הדין. lifnim mishurat
hadin. Maybe he thought he was
asking. Okay, so then he says wait a minute, זה לא עומד
וצווח. veze lo omed vetzoveiach. And this gets back to the case
of the middle of the ocean. This guy is saying I never
gave up hope. You're telling me I was מיאש miayeish because I
lost it in Grand Central Station. I'm telling you I never gave
up hope and I've been looking for it ever since. So how
can you tell me I was מיאש? miayeish? הגמרא ha-Gemara says נעשה
כצווח על ביתו שנפל ועל ספינתו שטבעה בים. na'aseh ketzoveiach al beiso
shenafal ve'al sefinato shetava beyam. Yeah,
it's good, a lot of people cry about things that are hopeless.
It's like you cried about the fact that your your your ship
sank and your house fell in. But bottom line is your wanting
to get it back is not considered, it's sort of like the
way some ראשונים Rishonim say it's בטלה דעתו אצל כל אדם. batlah
da'ato eitzel kol adam. Just because you think you want to get
it back, הלכה halacha refuses to recognize that as a realistic hope
and expectation. Okay, so if this is like you know, another way
of saying it is, is that if it's in a place where
it's definitely going to be lost, then we don't need יאוש. yeiush.
The reality that it's lost to you is enough to say that
you no longer own it regardless of the question of what's in
your mind. Okay, but here basically it's very important because we might
have lost sense of this. We wind up here now פסקנין paskenin
according to this פסק, psak, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar, the most extreme position. Even if it's רוב ישראל, rov Yisrael,
presumably because it was a marketplace of רבנן rabbanan according to one
interpretation, right? Nevertheless, we assume that the person gives up hope of
getting it back because some unscrupulous person will find it and even
if he's yelling and saying he's not giving up hope, we completely
ignore that. All right, so now let's just conclude this גמרא Gemara
without a סימן? siman? No, with a סימן. siman. Without a סימן
siman it's not a חידוש. chiddush. Yeah.
We have no obligation to find someone to return it?
If it's in a place of like a Grand Central Station type
of a place.
Okay,
now ההוא דיו דשקל בישרא
בשוקא hahu deiyo deshakeil bisra beshuka ושדייא בצינייתא דבי בר מריון. veshadya
betzinyasa devei Bar Maryon. So there was a like a vulture or
something that picked up a piece of meat and then threw it
in amongst the palm trees of בי בר מריון. bei Bar Maryon.
אתא לקמיה דאביי. Asa lekamei de-Abaye. Somebody found it. אמר ליה זיל
שקול לנפשך, Amar leh zil shekol lenafshach, keep it. והא רובא דישראל
נינהו? Veha ruba de-Yisrael ninhu? But I don't understand, it came from
a place, presumably the place where the vulture, I made up the
word vulture, I don't know what it says there. What does it
say? Vulture. Maybe the place where the vulture took it was majority
ישראל. Yisrael. שמעת מינה הלכה כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר אפילו ברוב ישראל?
Shemas minah halacha ke-Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar afilu berov Yisrael? Do we
see we פסקן pasken like him even by רוב ישראל? rov Yisrael?
No, שאני דיו דכזוטו של ים דמי. shani deiyo de-kezuto shel yam
dami. Forget about the place that he picked it up off the
ground. The reason it's מותר muttar is not because it was on
the ground and it was taken from the ground. The reason it's
מותר muttar is because it was taken by the vulture. Something in
the mouth of a vulture, you give up hope of ever getting
back. ואמר רבא בשר שנתעלם מן העין אסור. Ve-amar Rava basar shenisalem
min ha-ayin asur. I don't get it, how can you eat the
meat? Okay, once you have, once you lost sight of the meat,
we have to be suspicious about what type of meat it was.
בעומד ורואהו. Be-omed vero'ehu. No, you kept your eyes on it the
whole time and you saw where the vulture was going and you
saw where it dropped the meat, so therefore the meat is allowed.
Anyway, so that's basically, but it seems like we rule like רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar even by רוב ישראל. rov
Yisrael. I know it's already 8:32 but if you give me a
minute because it's actually the discussion, can we just go to the
bottom of the page, let's just do this in two minutes. רב
חנינא מצא גדי שחוט בין טבריה לציפורי. Rav Chanina matza gedi shachut
bein Teverya le-Tzippori. He found a slaughtered goat between טבריה Teverya and
ציפורי. Tzippori. והתירו לו, ve-hitiro lo, they permitted it to him.
אמר רבי אמי התירוהו משום מציאה, Amar Rabbi Ami hitirohu mishum metziah,
they let him keep it like a מציאה, metziah, משום כרבי שמעון
בן אלעזר, mishum ke-Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, because of רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. Presumably it was a place of where
a high traveled road or something so it was רוב rov even
with רוב ישראל. rov Yisrael.
But משום שחיטה, mishum shechitah, and not only that, nobody knew who
slaughtered it. He lost a live goat and they found it slaughtered.
And you could assume that the שוחט shochet was Jewish and knew
the הלכה. halacha. כרב חנינא בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי. ke-Rav Chanina
beno shel Rabbi Yosi Ha-Gelili. דתניא, detanya, הרי שאבדו לו גדייו ותרנגוליו,
harei she-avedu lo gedayav vesarnagolav, somebody lost his goat and his chicken,
והלך ומצאן שחוטין, vehalach umetzan shechutin, and he found them slaughtered. רבי
יהודה אוסר, Rabbi Yehuda oser, can you assume the שוחט shochet knew
what he was doing? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's forbidden. ורב
חנינא בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי מתיר. Ve-Rav Chanina beno shel Rabbi
Yosi Ha-Gelili matir. אמר רבי, Amar Rabbi, נראין דברי רבי יהודה כשמצאן
באשפה, nirein divrei Rabbi Yehuda keshemetzan be-ashpah, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda makes
sense if you found it in a dump because if somebody slaughtered
it maybe it was פסול pasul and therefore they threw it out
in the garbage place. ודברי רב חנינא בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי
כשמצאן בבית, Vedivrei Rav Chanina beno shel Rabbi Yosi Ha-Gelili keshemetzan be-vayis,
if you found it in a house because somebody maybe I don't
know stole it or whatever was going to eat it himself. תוספות
Tosafot basically says even if you're a גנב ganav doesn't mean you're
still מקפיד makpid on kosher.
I mean that's often an assumption here. So you found, so therefore
in that case it wasn't thrown out and it was slaughtered, you
can assume it was slaughtered properly. מכדי התירוהו משום שחיטה, Michdi hitirohu
mishum shechitah,
now from the fact that they're saying you can assume it was
slaughtered properly, רובא ישראל נינהו, ruba Yisrael ninhu, we have to assume
that most people in that locale were Jewish. שמעת מינה הלכה כרבי
שמעון בן אלעזר אפילו ברוב ישראל? Shemas minah halacha ke-Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar afilu berov Yisrael? And from there we can also infer and
then you said you could keep it as a מציאה, metziah, so
שמעת מינה הלכה כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר אפילו ברוב ישראל. shemas minah
halacha ke-Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar afilu berov Yisrael. We rule like רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar even if a majority is
ישראל. Yisrael. If it's presumably a high traveled road. אמר רבא לא.
Amar Rava lo. רוב נכרים ורוב טבחי ישראל. Rov nachrim verov tivchei
Yisrael. The majority of the population was not Jewish, but the majority
of the שוחטים shochtim were Jewish. So therefore the שחיטה shechitah you
could assume is good and the reason you could keep the מציאה
metziah is because you could assume that the person who lost it
was a non-Jew. רב אמי אשכח פרגיות שחוטות בין טבריא לציפורי Rav
Ami ashcach pargiyot shechutot bein Tverya leTzipori and he found slaughtered like
pigeons between Tiberias and Tzipori. אתא לקמיה דרב אסי Ata lekamei deRav
Assi ואמרי לה לקמיה דרבי יוחנן ve'amrei lah lekamei deRabbi Yochanan ואמרי
לה בבי מדרשא ve'amrei lah bevei midrasha they came to Rav Assi
or Rabbi Yochanan or they came to the Beit Midrash and they
said to him זיל שקול לנפשך zil shekol lenafshach keep it for
yourself. Okay but again it's not clear whether it's רוב נכרים rov
nachrim or whether you know it's just a high traffic area. רב
יצחק נפחא אשכח כבורא דאזלי
ביה אזלוני Rav Yitzchak Nafcha ashcach kibura de'azli bei azlunei so he
found this whatever the bundles of string that are used for making
nets for fishermen. אתא לקמיה דרבי יוחנן Ata lekamei deRabbi Yochanan he
came to Rabbi Yochanan ואמרי לה בבי מדרשא ve'amrei lah bevei midrasha
and they said to him ואמרו ליה זיל שקול לנפשך ve'amru leih
zil shekol lenafshach take it for yourself. So again what is the
general principle? Clearly it seems a general principle is the majority population
is not Jewish you're allowed to keep it. Although as was pointed
out there's a different type of לפנים משורת הדין lifnim mishurat hadin
there about דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. Okay but you're allowed to keep
it. What happens if it turns out that it actually did belong
to ישראל Yisrael and the person came and gave a סימן? siman?
There's one opinion before that says oh well then your assumptions were
wrong and you have to return it. But it seems that the
גמרא Gemara is saying like no you're still allowed to keep it.
Maybe there's a לפנים משורת הדין lifnim mishurat hadin and even though
you know now that it was Jewish that guy's lack of יאוש
ye'ush is not meaningful. He should have been מיאש meya'esh because it
was majority non-Jewish and he should have known you would have kept
it. Okay which is a pretty shocking thing although there still might
be a לפנים משורת הדין. lifnim mishurat hadin. What's the story if
it's a high traffic place and רוב ישראל? rov Yisrael? That we
haven't really clearly concluded. So if you have like a Jewish Times
Square okay you go into Israel and you go to some place
where like a Jewish Times Square what? כיכר שבת Kikar Shabbat or
whatever you go you know one of those types of places that's
a separate question whether there we assume that you're מיאש meya'esh regardless
just because maybe some unscrupulous person will keep it. Okay that's...